（序幕）
（极北之地 1857年）
船长！
Captain!
能聊聊吗？
Can we talk?
嗯
Hmm.
我们必须破冰前行
We must break through the ice.
大家都很饿 也累坏了
The men are hungry and exhausted.
要是继续这样下去 恐怕会付出代价
We cannot keep up this pace without consequence.
大家听着！
Listen up, men!
我们拖得越久 冰就冻得越牢固
The more we delay the labor, the firmer the grasp of the ice will become.
继续干活
The work continues.
各组轮流作业
Rotate each group.
先生 请听我说
Sir, with respect…
大家需要一句准话
The men need assurances.
准话？
Assurances?
对 就是让船动起来之后 我们会回圣彼得堡去
Yes, that we will head back to St. Petersburg once we free the ship.
他们觉得我们的船航行不了多久了 他们想知道…
They don't think we'll be seaworthy for long and they want to know--
都听好了！
Listen up!
别的任何事情 都不是你们和这位长官该考虑的
It is neither your place, nor the officer here, to think anything…
我们接受了一项任务 就要把它完成
We signed up for a mission and we will see it to completion.
我们一定会到达北极
We will reach the North Pole.
都听明白了吗？
Is it understood?
船长 那里爆炸了…
An explosion, Captain.
离这里大约三公里
About two miles away.
去救人
Get the men.
雪橇犬没受伤
The sled dogs are unharmed.
那这血是哪来的？
Then where does all this blood come from?
船长 在那里！
Over here, Captain!
有个受了伤的人 他流了好多血
A wounded man, he's lost a lot of blood.
肩膀受伤了 腿断了
Wound to the shoulder, his leg is broken.
是被熊咬的吗？
Bear attack?
我觉得不是 船长
I don't think so, Captain.
拉森 来帮我把这只靴子脱下来
Larsen, help me with his boot.
是个假肢
A prosthetic leg.
把他抬船上去
Put him on the board.
快 抬上船 赶紧！
Hurry! To the ship! Now!
拉森 那东西来了
Larsen, that thing is coming.
步枪准备！
Ready the rifles!
听我指令
On my command.
瞄准！
Aim!
开火！
Fire!
下一组！
Next group!
开火！
Fire!
全部上船！
All to the ship!!
我们抬上船的那个人呢？
Where is that man we brought onboard?
他在哪里？
Where?
那究竟是什么东西？它想干什么？
What is that thing? What does it want?
把他给我！
Bring him to me!
喇叭枪 拉森 拿喇叭枪！
The blunderbuss. Larsen, get the blunderbuss!
维克多
Victor.
维克多！
Victor!
我杀了它
I killed it.
它还活着！
It's still alive!
梯子！
Ladder!
快收梯子！
Pull up the ladder!
把他交出来！
Bring him to me!
还剩几发？
How many shots are left?
一发 但杀不了它
One, but it can't kill it.
我知道
I know.
我也不是要打他
I'm not aiming for him.
这是鸦片酊 能止痛 喝吧
Laudanum, to ease the pain. Drink it. Drink it.
我这是在哪里？
Where am I?
这是丹麦皇家航船霍莱松特号
You are on the Royal Danish ship, Horisont.
我是安德森船长 这位是邬德森医生
I'm Captain Anderson. This is Dr. Udsen.
那怪物杀了你们多少人？
How many of your men did it kill?
六个
Six.
它会回来 让更多人丧命
It will come back and kill many more.
要是不把我交出去 你们都会没命
All of you, if necessary, unless you deliver me to it.
不会的 它不在了
No, no. It's gone.
它沉入了冰水 死了
It sank in the freezing waters. It's dead.
它没死！
No, it is not!
它死不了
It cannot die.
我一直尝试彻底摧毁它
I have tried to destroy it.
不管你们信不信
Whether you believe me or not,
它都会回来 找我
it will come back… for me.
等它真的回来了
And when it does,
一定要把我送到外面的冰面上
you must promise that you will put me out on the ice
让它带走我
and let it take me.
求你们了
Please.
那究竟是什么？
What manner of creature is that?
是什么样的魔鬼造出来的？
What manner of devil made him?
是我
I did.
就是我
是我亲手造的他
I made him.
我本已下定决心 让那些罪恶的记忆和我一同消亡
I had determined that the memory of my evils should die with me.
准备好了
It's ready.
接下来我要说的话 有些是真的
Some of what I will tell you is fact.
有些是假的 但这是真的
Some is not, but it is all true.
我叫维克多
My name is Victor.
维克多·弗兰肯斯坦
Victor Frankenstein.
我的名字是父亲起的
It was my father who gave me that name.
你知道这名字是什么意思吗？
Do you know what it means?
应该是征服者的意思
I believe I do, yes. Conqueror.
赢得一切的人
One that wins it all.
没错 一切因他而起
Yes. It all started with him.
我的父亲
My father.
还有我的母亲
And my mother.
维克多！
Victor!
（第一部分 维克多的故事）
维克多！
Victor!
快下来 你父亲来了
Come down, your father is arriving.
Maman?
母亲 我在这里
I'm here, Mother.
这里
I'm here.
我父亲是男爵 也是个杰出的外科医生
My father was a baron and a preeminent surgeon.
他娶我母亲 很大程度上为了利益
He had married my mother largely out of convenience,
因为母亲的陪嫁相当丰厚 而且她是贵族出身
as her dowry was considerable and her lineage noble.
她带来的资金 足以让父亲维持爵位和家族产业
It furnished my father with the means to preserve his rank and family estate.
日常生活中 从来看不见父亲的身影
He was absent from our lives,
而每当他回到家 所有人都对他唯命是从
but when he came home, the entire household bent to his will.
亲爱的克莱尔
Claire, dear.
他不在的时候…
The rest of the time…
维克多
Victor.
父亲
Father.
他不在的时候 母亲就是我一个人的
The rest of the time, Mother was mine.
别拿走 端到这里来
No, bring that here.
肉里的盐分能滋养你的血液
The salts in the meat will enrich your blood,
还有胎儿的
as well as the baby's.
一人吃 两人补 记得吗？
You eat for two, remember?
吃吧
Go on.
很有营养
It's nutritious.
守护天使
Guardian angel.
甜蜜的陪伴
Sweet companion.
请守护我 不要离开我
Stand by my side and do not leave me.
用你的披风庇护我 然后…
Under your mantle, shelter me, and…
我隔着墙听到他们争论不休
I would hear them through the wall, arguing incessantly,
对着彼此大吼大叫 话题关于财富和庄园 还有我
yelling at each other about wealth, estate… and me.
他们的争吵声让我万分恐惧
Their voices filled me with fear.
Maman?
那个男人鄙视我们两个
The man despised us both.
讨厌我们乌黑的头发、深色的瞳孔
Our raven black hair, our deep, dark eyes.
就连我们喜好安静、不时紧张的性情
Even our quiet, at times nervous disposition
似乎也会让他大为光火
seemed to exasperate him to no end.
古代把体液分为哪几类？
List as accurately as you can the ancient classification
尽量说精确一点
of the humors in the human body.
血液、黑胆汁、黄胆汁和黏液
Blood, black bile, yellow bile, and phlegm.
男性心脏的平均重量是多少？
Average male heart. Weight?
250到310克 父亲
Nine to eleven ounces, Father.
女性心脏的平均重量？
Average female heart. Weight?
230到280克
Eight to ten ounces.
你为什么觉得
Why do you suppose that is?
女性的心脏会轻一点？
Difference in mass in female heart?
是因为她们情感更强烈？
Depth of emotion?
更容易忧郁吗？
Tendency to the melancholic?
因为质量 血流量 肌肉灌注的不同 父亲
Mass. Volume of blood, Father. Muscular irrigation.
没错 人体组织中没有精神物质
Quite. There is no spiritual content in tissue,
肌肉中没有情感
and no emotion in a muscle.
那么 请描述一下三尖瓣的主要功能
Now, describe the main function of the tricuspid valve, please.
我现在想不起来了 父亲 但我肯定能想起来
I cannot recall, Father, but I'm sure I will remember.
嗯 我相信你
Yeah, I'm sure you will.
象牙不会流血 维克多
Ivory does not bleed, Victor.
但人体会
Flesh does.
等你想起了某个知识要点 恐怕你的病人已经一命呜呼了
By the time you remember a fact, your patient could be dead.
懂了吗？
You understand?
三尖瓣的主要功能
The main function of the tricuspid valve
是防止血液反流至腔静脉
is to prevent the reflux of blood into the vena cava.
不打手了 再也不打了
No, not your hands. Not anymore.
它们如今是你施展技艺的工具 是你意志的延伸
They are now the instruments of your craft and will,
要好好保护
and we must care for them.
而你的脸 就微不足道了
Your face, however, is vanity.
维克多 你沿用了我的名字 也必然要维护我的名声
You bear my name, Victor, and with it my reputation.
我恳请你牢记这一点
I pray you remember that.
我感觉你有很好的牌
I feel you have something very good, parce que…
三
Three…
二
Two…
一
One…
不可能
That's impossible.
我来洗牌
I'll shuffle.
母亲？
Mother?
Maman?\Maman?
父亲
Father!
父亲 母亲出事了
Father. It's Mother.
Maman.\Maman.
准备好热水和干净的亚麻布 多拿一点 快
I need hot water and clean linen. A lot of it.
是 先生
-Now. -Sir.
-不 维克多 -妈妈？
-No, Victor! -Mother?
-Maman! -维克多!
-Maman! -Victor!
父亲！
Father! Father!
一定要救她 求你了！
-Victor! -Save her, please!
我的母亲 我曾将她视作我的一部分
My mother, whom I had come to consider a part of my very self,
我曾以为她永远不会离去
she who I thought would never leave,
以为她是我的生命 如今她死了
she who was life… was now death.
她的双眼已暗淡无光
Her eyes extinguished,
笑容被冰冷的土地埋葬
her smile feeding the cold earth.
走开！
Leave!
都给我走开！
All of you, leave!
我的世界空了一块
A part of the universe had been hollowed out
我的头顶笼罩着永远的黑暗
and the firmament was now permanently dark.
遮住眼睛
Now, cover your eyes.
我叫你看再看哦
Don't look until I tell you to.
看吧
Now.
威廉在阳光和笑容中长大
William grew full of sunshine and smiles.
他的性情比我平和温顺 显然更讨父亲喜欢
He was of a calmer, gentler disposition, clearly favored by my father.
谢谢你 父亲
Thank you, Father.
不客气 儿子
Oh, it's a pleasure, my boy.
他是宜人的微风 我是滚滚的黑云
He was the breeze, I was the storm cloud.
他带来欢声笑语 我让人愁眉不展
He was all laughter, I was all frowns.
拿起缰绳
Pick up the reins.
父亲 看我做得怎么样
Look at me, Father. Look at me.
不止如此
There was something more.
更确切地说 某些东西被忽视了
Or rather, something was missing.
我的母亲
My mother had died
死在如日中天的名医
at the hands of the most distinguished doctor of his day:
我的父亲手下
My father.
我的脑中渐渐有了个想法
An idea… took shape in my mind.
请说说《心血运动论》中…
Define the circulatory system, if you will…
无可避免 无法逃避
Inevitable, unavoidable…
…对循环系统是怎么定义的
…as enunciated in De Motu Cordis.
…直到这个想法被说了出来
…until it became truth.
父亲？
Father?
你没救她 对吗？
You let her die, did you not?
我用尽全力救她了 你必须知道这一点
I did everything in my power to save her. You must know that.
这么说 你失败了
So you failed.
没人能战胜死亡
-No one can conquer death. -Mm-hmm.
我能 我会战胜的
I will. I will conquer it.
我会掌握你掌握的所有知识 还会更进一步
Everything you know, I will know. And more.
今天就到此为止吧
I think we've done quite enough for today.
那晚我重生了
I was born anew that night.
我看到了幻象
I had a vision.
我第一次看到了
I saw, for the first time…
黑暗天使
the Dark Angel.
它向我许下承诺
And it made me a promise.
我将能掌控生死
I would have command over the forces of life and death.
成为和父亲一样杰出的外科医生
I would become every ounce the surgeon my father was.
我的野心和成就将超过他
I would surpass him in ambition and in reach.
守护天使…
幻象如此清晰
The vision was so clear.
无论清醒还是睡梦中 我都从未看到如此清晰的景象
Clearer than anything I'd ever seen in my waking hours or dreams.
但承诺如何兑现？
But how?
我的境遇很快一落千丈
My downfall was swift.
母亲的种植园 经历了两次叛乱和一场火灾
Two revolts and a fire on my mother's plantations
家族财富因此锐减
dwindled the family fortune.
庄园留下了 但别的全都没了
We kept the estate, but lost everything else.
威廉被送去了维也纳的亲戚家
William went to one side of the family in Vienna
我去了伦敦 然后又去了爱丁堡
and I to London, then Edinburgh.
在那里 我花了数十年时间
And there, for decades, I tried to…
尝试为狭隘的学术界拓宽边界
expand the narrow limits of academia.
生命
Life.
这就是生命 先生们
This… is life, gentlemen.
（皇家医学院纪律法庭 1855年）
我们出生了
We are born.
嗯?
Hmm?
刚上去没多久 就掉下来了
And no sooner do we rise, we fall.
死了
Death.
这一起一落之间
And in the space between that rise and fall,
就是我们渺小卑微的一生
our humble little purview.
出生不为我们所控
Now, birth is not in our hands.
对不对？
Is it?
生命之火的点燃 思想和灵魂的诞生
Conception, that spark, the animation of thought and soul.
掌握在上帝的手中
That is in God's hands.
上帝
God.
而死亡
But death.
挑战正在此处
Ah, now there lies the challenge.
死亡应该掌握在我们手中
That should be our concern.
应该如此
It should be.
我们凭什么能掌控？ 我们又不是神明 对不对？
Who are we to do so? We are not gods, are we?
但要是我们能像神明那般大胆
But if we are to behave as immodestly as gods,
那至少能够创造奇迹
we must, at the very least, deliver miracles.
是不是？
Wouldn't you say?
在年轻学子心中点燃神圣火花
Ignite a divine spark…in these young students' minds.
教导他们抛弃顺从 违抗权威
Teach them defiance rather than obedience.
展示人类有可能掌控自然奥秘 让死亡不再发生
Show that man may pursue nature to her hiding places and stop death.
不是延缓死亡 而是长生不老！
Not slow it down, but stop it entirely!
安静！
Silence. Silence!
这种不可能的事 你究竟要怎么教？
How exactly do you propose to teach what is impossible?
人类的尸体 一个复合实体
Composite subject, the body.
这是某个店老板 刚咽气没多久就送到了我这里
That of a shopkeeper, delivered mere moments after expiration.
大脑暴露在外 但仍能运作
The brain laid bare but functional,
脊神经分支和迷走神经完好无损
the spinal branches and vagal nerves intact.
大家或许能看到一些极细的伤口
You may observe the hair-thin scars.
我的手艺无需粗糙的缝合
No coarse stitching needed by my own technique.
看这条手臂
The arm, you see,
来自某个木匠
comes from another specimen, that of a carpenter.
肌肉、韧带、神经 都已连结好
The muscles, ligaments, nerves, all connected now.
看啊 电流导致躯体痉挛
Now, the spasmodic movement of the body
这已不是新鲜事
caused from the electric current, this is not new.
大家都见过 不过 这种躯体内的能量流动
It's not new. However, the flow of energy through the body
遵循一种完全不同的概念
follows a different notion entirely.
一种称为气的东方概念
An Eastern notion called qi.
这种概念认为 生命能量的流动 同时存在于身体内外
Now, it considers the vital flow of energy both within and without.
我用针在六个…
I'm utilizing needles in six--
安静！都坐下！
Quiet! Sit down!
医生 这是听证会 不是狂欢节表演
This is a hearing, Doctor, not a carnival act.
你这样无济于事 维克多
You're not helping your cause, Victor.
这种用电的诡计根本没用
This galvanic trickery will simply not do.
诡计
Trickery.
诡计？
Trickery?
你确定吗？
Are you sure?
这不是诡计 而是一种抉择
That is not trickery. That is a decision.
一个死人的眼睛 和另一个死人的胳膊协调运动
Motor coordination between the eye of one dead man and the arm of another,
注入全新的意志和基本的理解力
infused with a new will and the rudiments of understanding.
已经死亡的大脑也有理解力吗？
Understanding in a brain that already died?
放开
Release now.
请放开
Please.
礼貌一点总有效果
"Please" always helps.
赶紧关了吧 你个江湖骗子
Turn that off at once. At once, you charlatan.
这就是未来 这是有可能实现的
This is the future. This is possible.
为什么不研究一下 量化一下呢？
Why not study it? Why not quantify it?
这是罪恶的 可恨、下流！
This is unholy. An abomination. An obscenity!
生命由上帝赐予 由上帝收回 维克多
God gives life, and God takes it, Victor.
或许上帝就是无能！
Perhaps God is inept!
要由我们来纠正他的错误！
And it is we that must amend his mistakes!
别让这些老蠢货阻止你自由表达！
Do not let these old fools extinguish your voice!
只有采取不盲从的态度 摆脱恐惧和恃强凌弱的教条
The answers only come when coaxed by disobedience,
答案才会浮现！
free of fear and cowardly dogma!
克伦佩教授
Professor Krempe.
弗兰肯斯坦男爵 我叫海因里希·哈兰德
Baron Frankenstein, my name is Heinrich Harlander,
我这里有一封
and I carry with me a letter of introduction
你的弟弟威廉写的介绍信
from your brother, William.
我弟弟？
From my brother?
我希望能有幸认识你
I asked for the privilege of your acquaintance.
耽误你一点时间
It won't take but a minute of your time.
-请进 -好
-Please. -Very well.
这么说 威廉要来看我 对吗？
So William is coming to see me, is that it?
对 几天后到
Yeah, in a matter of days.
他想让你见见他的未婚妻 也就是我的侄女
He wants to introduce you to his fiancée. My niece, as it happens.
她叫伊丽莎白·哈兰德 是一位非常可爱的小姐
Elizabeth Harlander, a very nice young lady,
刚刚从修道院学校毕业
fresh from convent life.
这些照片都是我拍的
The photographs are mine.
威廉在金融领域很有成就
William has become quite successful in the world of finance.
弗兰肯斯坦的名声越来越响了
He's making a name for himself.
哎哟！是吗？
Ha! A name? For himself?
要知道我们都是弗兰肯斯坦 不管我们乐不乐意
Well, I'm afraid we both share that name, whether we like it or not.
我拜读了你在《柳叶刀》上的文章
I read your article in The Lancet.
你真的觉得这事能做到吗？
You really believe you can do it?
组装出一个人来？
Assemble a man?
做出完整的全新人体？还要有生命？
A full new body? And give it life?
你今天也看到了
You saw it today, didn't you?
说真的 我看到的是你当众受难
What I saw was a crucifixion, really.
你还没开口说句话 就被钉死了
You were done for before you uttered a word.
但我还是向他们展示了
I still showed them.
展示什么？
What?
事实
The truth.
他们到晚餐时间就忘了
They will forget by suppertime.
话虽如此 你觉得怎么样？
Yes, yes, yes. But what did you think? Hmm?
我觉得非常厉害
I thought it was brilliant.
没错 我就知道
It was. I know.
但你有点孩子气 太激动了
But you are like a child, so excited,
紧抓你的新宠物 快把它勒死了
clutching your new pet so tightly that you're strangling it.
我不免为你担心
That is why I worry about you.
你能控制好火种吗 普罗米修斯？
Can you contain your fire, Prometheus?
还是没等把它交出去 就先烧伤了自己的手？
Or are you going to burn your hands before delivering it?
说得对
Quite.
请不要觉得我无礼 但这一天已经足够漫长
Please do not think me rude, but my day has proven long enough,
我的状态也完全不适合 再陪伴陌生人了
and I believe myself totally unfit for the company of strangers.
如果没有什么别的事了…
So if there's nothing more--
还有重要的事
Oh, but there is. Much more.
我在爱丁堡找好了住处
I've taken quarters in Edinburgh.
三天后 我们一起见威廉和伊丽莎白
Three days from now, we are to meet with William and Elizabeth.
我将在那晚改变你的命运
And that evening, I will change your destiny.
我会让你看到非同凡响的东西
I will show you something extraordinary.
-你真好 -谢谢 给
桃子 把桃子转过来
The peach. The peach. Turn the peach. Turn it.
你又啃了
You bit it again.
你一直在吃桃
You're eating the peaches.
这是对死亡的沉思
This is a memento mori.
桃子是生命和青春的符号 怎么就被你啃了？
The peach, symbol of life and youth, and you bite into it?
-我饿了呀 小希 -别那样叫我
-I was hungry, Kiki. -Don't call me Kiki.
先生 维克多·弗兰肯斯坦男爵来了
Baron Victor Frankenstein, sir.
你可以下去了
You can leave.
抱歉
Forgive me.
欢迎
Welcome.
哈兰德先生
Herr Harlander.
这是一种新兴艺术 摄影
A young art, photography.
再见 小希
Goodbye, Kiki.
我已经迷上了
Already a passion of mine.
文件都带来了吗？
Did you bring the papers?
谢谢
Oh, thank you.
-你非常出色 -谢谢
-You're extraordinary. -Thank you.
嗯
Hmm.
你利用神经系统来传递能量脉冲
You're using the nervous system to deliver the surge of energy.
对吗？
Are you not?
没错
Correct.
因此 你所操控的生命力 只能维持很短时间
And thus the sustainability of the life force you command
很快就会衰退、消散
is very brief, wanes, evaporates.
为什么这么说？
How so?
当时你颇为自豪地结束了演示
At the lecture, you ended your demonstration out of pride.
但其实是因为 那股电流般的生命力
But really, because the galvanic life force
已经衰竭了 对吗？
was already fading, was it not?
先生 你是外科医生吗？
Are you yourself a surgeon, sir?
曾经是 我是战地医生
Yeah, once upon a time. An army surgeon.
医术也说不上多精湛
Not a particularly skilled one, either.
但也给我打下了发家致富的基础
But it allowed me to secure the rudiments of my fortune.
我现在有几家军火工厂
I own a few ammunition factories.
-你是军火商 -不如说是个务实的
-An arms merchant. -A realist.
你对伊夫林解剖图表熟悉吗？
Are you familiar with the Evelyn Tables?
当然 那是约翰·伊夫林爵士当年
Of course. Acquired by Sir John Evelyn,
买下的四张人体标本精细解剖图
there are four planks, meticulous dissection,
是欧洲最早的人体神经 和动静脉解剖图
some of the oldest in Europe, presenting the nerves,
为什么会提到这个？
veins and arteries of cadavers. What?
因为还有第五张
Yes. But there's a fifth one.
这张最让人信服
The most compelling one.
非常细致 是不是？
Exquisite, is it not?
呈现于木头上的鲜活血肉
Flesh rendered onto wood.
尸体放在木板上 逐层剥离
The cadaver lies on the plank, is peeled away layer by layer,
用树脂将剩下的组织固定在木板上
and the remaining tissue is lacquered with resin onto the wood.
-这是淋巴系统 -没错
-It showcases the lymphatic system. -Yes.
穆斯林医学家称其为隐秘的循环系统
Muslim medics called it the secret circulatory system.
仅仅输送三升体液 却构成了庞大的网络
It moves a mere three liters of fluid, but it's a vast network.
-真是非同凡响 -确实
-Oh, it's remarkable. -Yes.
现在对我们 也是对你而言 关键的改变就在这里
Now for us, for you, the important variation is here.
这第九种构造 环绕心脏的结构
The ninth configuration. A very delicate,
极为精巧 近乎空灵
almost ethereal structure surrounding the heart.
既能分配能量 也能储存能量
It can distribute, but also store energy.
如果你能在不破坏周围组织的前提下
Yes, if you can access that without destroying
-触达这一构造… -不 不是前面
-the surrounding tissue-- -No. Not through the front.
是后面 脊柱 胸曲
The back, spinal column, thoracic curvature.
没错
Of course.
远超人们想象的能量流动 瘢痕形成和组织再生
Flow of energy, scarring and regeneration beyond anyone's imagination.
永生
Life eternal.
我将提供无限的资源 来支持你的研究
I will endow your pursuit with unlimited resources.
那我要拿什么来交换？
And in exchange?
这么说就俗了
No need to become indelicate.
我们探寻真理 志在超越 有着共同的追求
We're searchers for truth and transcendence, kindred spirits.
某天我也许会请你帮个忙 作为回报
I may in time ask you for a favor in return,
但最重要的是记录研究过程 以传诸后世的这份特权
but it's mostly the privilege to record your process for posterity.
我习惯独自工作
I work alone.
我绝对不出声
I'm very quiet.
哈兰德先生 威廉·弗兰肯斯坦和您的侄女到了
William Frankenstein and your niece, Herr Harlander.
我要考虑一下
I shall consider it.
我会考虑的
I'll consider it.
男爵
Baron.
别假装冷静了 错过了就可惜了
Don't pretend to be reasonable now. It would be such a shame.
维克多
Victor.
威廉！
William!
-维克多 -瞧瞧你
-Victor. -Look at you.
老天 你长大了
My, you've grown.
可惜不是我的功劳
Through no merit of my own.
来见见我的未婚妻吧
May I introduce the woman I'm to marry.
伊丽莎白·哈兰德小姐
Lady Elizabeth Harlander.
荣幸之至
Absolutely delighted.
听到你被驱逐 说实话我也不惊讶
Can't say I was shocked when you were expelled,
但他们的态度太强硬 言语太狠毒
but the manner and virulence of your expulsion,
我认为实在没有必要
uncalled for, I'm sure.
有必要
No, it was called for.
我应得的
I earned it.
我特意挣来的 你说是不是 哈兰德先生？
I made it a point to earn it, wouldn't you say, Herr Harlander?
确实声势浩大
It was quite an exit, I assure you.
为什么要激怒他们？
Why provoke them?
何不继续做自己的事 避免惹来不必要的关注？
Why not just carry on without calling attention to yourself in such a manner?
威廉 就算以你的标准来看 这么做也太保守了
How safe, even by your standards, William.
你这话听着都有点像父亲了
You almost sound like Father.
父亲可是相当老练的
He was a most tactful man, our father.
他做事精准、谨慎、有分寸感
He was precise, discreet, measured.
我就不是 我完全不懂为何谦虚是一种美德
I, on the other hand, fail to see why modesty is considered a virtue at all.
维克多一直这么引人注目
Victor's always been one to harvest attention.
即便在小时候 我也常常 通过保持沉默 来消解他的声音
Even as children, I mitigated his voice by staying silent.
这样的事发生无数次了吧 维克多 你说呢？
Perhaps too much and far too many times, wouldn't you say, Victor?
如果可以再造生命
If life can be regenerated,
并非简单的模拟
not as a mere simulation,
而是通过物理化学手段 如神迹般地再造 何不大声说出来？
but as a divine act by physical, chemical means, why whisper it?
你笑了？
You laugh?
-你觉得好笑吗？ -没错
-You're amused? -I must be, yes.
我的理念没表达清楚吗？
Are my ideas not clear?
你显然已经够大声的了
You certainly expressed them loudly enough.
不值得为之努力吗？
Are they not worthwhile?
我认为理念本身并不值得为之努力
Ideas are not worthwhile by themselves, I don't believe.
愿闻其详
Enlighten me, please.
拿战争来说
Take the war, for example.
威廉 去书房享用雪茄和白兰地吧
William, cigar and brandy in my study?
我侄女的长篇大论你肯定都听过了
Surely you've heard my niece expound on the matter before.
我们失陪了
You'll excuse us.
请继续说 关于理念
Pray, carry on. Ideas.
这么说吧 荣耀、国家、勇气
Well… honor, country, valor.
这些必然是值得为之奋斗的崇高理念
These surely are worthwhile, elevated ideas by themselves,
同意吧？
wouldn't you agree?
然而 人们为了这些理念赴死
-Mm-hmm. -And nevertheless, men are dying for them.
以一种显然毫不崇高的方式
In a decidedly un-elevated way,
脸埋在泥泞里 喉咙呛着血
face down in the mud, choking on blood,
痛得大喊大叫
screaming in pain.
他们是某人的父亲、兄弟或儿子
Men that were fathers, brothers or sons to someone out there.
他们被自己的母亲带到这个世界
Men that were fed, cleaned and nursed
被悉心喂养、洗净、照料、教育
and schooled into this world by their mothers,
最后却被送到某个遥远的战场
only to fall on a battlefield far away,
真正制造惨剧的人却躲得远远的
far from those that provoke these tragedies.
他们好好地待在家中 不沾血 不挨刀
Those men remain at home, untouched by blood or bayonet,
皮肤完好无损 被窝温暖洁净
their skin unpierced, their blankets warm and clean.
这就是蠢人追求理念的后果
That is what happens when ideas are pursued by fools.
那你觉得我是蠢人
And you think me a fool?
嗯?
Hmm?
快享用你的白兰地和雪茄去吧
Run to your brandy and cigars.
他们都在等着呢
The boys are waiting.
一个人常常以为遇见了天使或魔鬼
How often a man believes he's met an angel or a devil,
到头来却发现一切不过是幻觉
only to find it is all an illusion.
我们下的这盘棋
The game of chess we play…
对手只有自己
we play only against ourselves.
帮帮他
Help him.
快点！
Help him!
给 喝点吧
Here you go. Drink some.
快跟我来
You better come with me.
什么都没有
Nothing.
先生 看守人看到他了
Sir, the watchman saw him.
在迷雾中绕着船转
Circling the ship. In the mist.
我们都亲眼看他沉下去了
We all saw him drown.
先生
Sir.
大家都很恐慌
The men are terrified.
觉得该把那个男人扔到冰面上
They think that man should be surrendered to the ice
结束这一切
and be done with this.
他受我保护…
He is under my protection…
受王国庇佑！
and the protection of the Crown!
几周后 我、威廉和哈兰德 骑马穿过海峡
A few weeks later, I rode with William and Harlander
来到瓦杜兹附近的一个湖边
to a lake near Vaduz across the channel.
这座塔楼是用来过滤农田灌溉用水的
The tower was built as a water filtration plant to irrigate the fields.
是个公共工程项目 所以战争一开始就被弃建了
Public works, so construction was abandoned at the start of the war.
不是这场战争 是前一场
Not this war, the one before.
或者是再前面一场 我记不清了
Or the one before that, I cannot quite remember.
一看到它
The moment I laid eyes on it…
这座塔楼
The tower.
我便感受到了命运的召唤
I could feel destiny calling.
建筑结构基本完整
The structure's basically intact.
这里还有一条陡坡道 从顶上直通到底部
And there's a chute going from top, right to the bottom.
我会安排人把你的个人物品
I can arrange for your belongings.
从爱丁堡运过来
We'll bring them from Edinburgh.
你需要什么 都能满足
Anything you need or want shall be granted.
-什么都可以？ -什么都可以
-Anything? -Anything.
整个项目期间 威廉随叫随到
I have secured William's service for the duration of the project.
我要一个临时密室
I'll need a holding cell.
-实验室旁边要有个冷库 -威廉
-And an ice chamber close to the lab. -William.
塔楼底部有两个泵水库
There are two pump reservoirs at the base of the tower.
要改造一下
We'll repurpose those.
我们要重启蒸汽机
We shall need to recondition the steam engines.
需要足够的燃料 来保证机器正常运转
We'll need enough fuel to make sure they run.
那里 还有那里 放四块高容量的伏打电池
There and there, four high-capacity voltaic batteries,
正负电极
positive and negative polarity,
还要一套纯银避雷针系统 向下延伸至实验室
and a lightning rod system of pure silver telescoping down into the lab.
没问题 你需要什么设备 我的承包商都能造出来
Yes. My contractors can manufacture any and all equipment you may require.
那么 我们应该达成共识了吧？
I take it then that we have an understanding?
交易达成
A bargain has been struck.
混蛋！
Bastard!
这个不行
No. No. Not this one.
张嘴
Aah. Open your mouth.
被绞死算你走运 你本就活不过今年了
You, you're lucky to be hanged. You would have died within the year.
哈兰德先生答应我 让我拿到最好的样本
Herr Harlander promised me access to optimal specimens.
阁下 他倒是答应了
Yeah, that he may have, your lordship,
可您也知道
but as you well know,
犯罪又不是什么好差事 我们这里也只有些歪瓜裂枣
crime doesn't pay, and it's a poor showing of it we have here.
哪个都是可怜虫
They're wretches every one of them.
真是抱歉
I'm sorry about that.
背很强壮 这个可以
That's a strong back. This one will do.
稍后再来
Come back later.
来告解？
Confession?
我很好奇
I was intrigued.
如此纤弱又虔诚的人 能有什么要告解的？
What would such a delicate, pious creature have to confess to?
真是碰巧 被我找到了一个机会
As luck would have it, an opportunity presented itself,
我…
and I…
我就要揭开谜底了
I was about to find out.
神父 请为我祝福 我有罪
Bless me, Father, for I have sinned.
孩子 你多久没告解了？
How long has it been since your last confession, my daughter?
还没到一周 神父 我在修道院待过
Barely a week, Father. I was in a convent.
就一周？
A week?
你就这么轻率地犯错了？
Tsk-tsk. Have you so hastily committed sin?
是的
I have.
是罪孽的念头 并非实际行动
Sin of intent, not deed.
-因为一名男子 对不对？ -对
-A man, is it? -Yes.
是我未婚夫的兄长
My fiancé's brother.
是欲念吗？
Lust?
是憎恶
Hatred.
憎恶…
Hatred…
-憎恶？ -那名男子很恶劣、很丑陋
-Hatred? -The man is appalling, grotesque.
这样的话很是刺耳
Harsh words.
近乎无情了 对吗？
Rather uncharitable, wouldn't you say?
尊敬的神父 您并不了解这个人
Respectfully, Father, you do not know this man.
他试图操控周围一切的人和事
He tries to control and manipulate everything and everyone around him.
他和所有暴君一样 以假扮受害者为乐
Like every tyrant, he delights in playing the victim.
要我说 那是他唯一的本事
His only advantage, I would say,
他自以为绅士 实则粗鄙不堪
is he's far cruder than he believes himself to be.
粗鄙不堪？
Cruder?
我的孩子 请详细说明
Uh, pray explain yourself, my child.
比如说 他太容易被发现了
For one, he's easy to spot.
即便是集市日的拥挤街道上 也能轻松看到他
You can see him… even on a busy street on market day.
说吧 你什么时候发现我的？
Tell me, how soon did you spot me?
只能说远比你看到我来得早
I saw you well before you saw me, I can say that much.
你吃过晚饭了吗？
Have you had supper?
我还不怎么饿 男爵 谢谢
I'm not that hungry, Baron. Thank you.
我就饿坏了
Well, I for one am famished.
-谢谢 好心人 -谢谢 先生
-Thank you, my good man. -Thank you, sir.
你买了什么书？能让我看看吗？
What books did you buy, hmm? May I?
你猜
Guess.
-让我猜？ -还是猜一下吧
-Guess? -Mm-hmm. I'd rather that you did.
那好
Very well.
言情小说
A romance…
沐浴着地中海的阳光 身着丝绸华服 沉醉于爱的纠葛
drenched in Mediterranean sun and silk and the skirmishes of love.
真是无礼 但也不奇怪
Insulting, but unsurprising.
是吗？
Really?
昆虫？
-Insects? -Mm.
我对科学的兴趣 体现在对微小生物的好奇上
My interest in science leans towards the smallest things.
它们随自然而动 或许是顺应上帝的节律
Moving with nature, perhaps the rhythms of God.
我一直在寻觅 某种更纯粹、更奇妙的事物
I've always searched for something more pure, marvelous.
这就是你在修道院追寻的东西吗？
Is that what you were seeking in the convent?
算是吧
In a way.
值得吗？
Was it worth it?
有什么是值得的吗？
Is anything?
可以吗？
Permit me, sister.
这样好像不大合适
This hardly seems appropriate.
有什么是合适的吗？
Is anything?
很好
Very well.
笑起来！
Laughter!
生平第一次
And for the very first time,
不知何故 我对生的兴趣渐浓
I became more interested in life
对死的兴趣
and somewhat less interested
减淡了
in death.
主杆采用快速螺栓固定系统
The main rod has a fast bolting system.
用合金了吗？
Did you use an alloy?
铜锌合金
Copper and zinc.
这个不行 重来吧
This is… This simply will not do. Start over.
纯银是完美的导体
Pure silver is a perfect conductor.
威廉 你得留下 拜托了
William, you must stay behind. Please.
我最信任的就是你了
I trust you above anyone else.
再多待几天就行
Only for a few more days.
你抓不到它的
You're not going to catch her.
真漂亮
Beautiful. Beautiful.
把它关起来 还是放走呢？
-Should we trap her or let her go? -Mm…
关起来
Trap her.
这下我们有共同点了
Now we have something in common.
一个囚徒
A prisoner.
威廉如约行事 认真负责建造实验室 满足各种需求
As promised, William took dutiful charge of the laboratory build and needs.
那边能修一下吗？
Can you fix that over there, please?
去帮一下
Go, help.
他严格按我的指示办事
He followed my instructions to the letter.
电池
The battery.
现在是纯银的了
It's all pure silver now.
这是和淋巴系统相对应的传导点
Conduction points corresponding to the lymphatic system,
非常复杂 但我做出来了
which was quite complex. -But I managed.
嗯哼
Mm-hmm.
哈兰德先生 谢谢 派对很精彩
Herr Harlander, thank you. The party's delightful.
但愿我们没有干扰你做研究
I hope we're not distracting you from your research
毕竟你还要顾着我和伊丽莎白
to tend to me and Elizabeth.
完全没有
Not at all.
她还年轻 我们得护着她
She's young. She can count on us to guard her.
我还是回避一下
I shall leave you your privacy.
我们之间还掩饰什么
No need for subterfuge between us.
法国陶瓷 多么美妙的共响
French porcelain, chimes to a man's stream.
我快找到解决方法了 给淋巴系统确定传导点
I am very near a solution, an access point to the lymphatic system.
哦 那个呀
Ah, yeah, that.
这么久了
It's been so long.
仗快打完了
The war is waning.
资金供应也快断了
And my funding will end with it.
你不是说资金无限供应吗？
You said your funds were unlimited.
但我的耐心是有限的
My patience is not.
我得到了可靠消息 一周内会爆发一场战斗
I have it on good authority that a battle is to take place within a week.
战争好比潮水 会把战利品送到我们这条海岸上来
The tide of war will deliver its bounty to our shore.
战场上的尸体肯定一塌糊涂
A battlefield? The bodies will be mangled.
就一周
One week.
-一周？ -一周后 创造历史的机会就会溜走
-One week? -After that, history will pass us by.
帮我冲一下吧 男爵
Flush that for me, will you, Baron?
一周内找到传递电流的办法
A week to determine how to deliver the current.
绝无可能
Impossible.
我该怎么办？
What would I do?
就快成功了 我感觉得到
I was close. I could feel it.
谁知横生阻碍
And then…life got in the way.
哦
Oh.
它肯定想你了
I believe she missed you.
伊丽莎白 我得先警告你一下 我在处理解剖体
I must warn you, Elizabeth, I've been working on a dissection.
很美
It's beautiful.
吓到你了吗？
Does it shock you?
让我想起了殉道主题的绘画
Reminds me of martyrdom paintings.
没有了痛苦
Pain is gone.
在对称的构造和形状中 看得到上帝的精妙手笔
You can see God's design in the symmetry and the shapes.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
我得向你坦白
I must confess something to you.
我相信这世间存在奇妙非凡之物 你也一样
I have a belief in the marvelous and so do you.
我们之间有种默契 你能感觉到吗？
There is a bond between us. Can you feel it?
一种近乎生理上的吸引 我坚信这种感觉绝非寻常
An almost physical one. I truly believe it to be something else.
你所信之物 未必是事实
Believing something does not make it true.
那你为什么来这里？
Then why are you here?
它很美 对不对？
Beautiful creature, is she not?
孤傲 令人沉迷 却又如此怪异
Remote. Entirely bewitching, but so odd.
有三颗心
Three hearts.
复眼 白色的血
Multiple eyes. White blood.
它无法做出选择 所以如此迷人
And a fascinating lack of choice.
我不明白
I don't understand.
有选择的能力 灵魂才能栖息
Choice is the seat of the soul.
这是上帝对我们的赠礼
The one gift God granted us.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth…
我做出选择了
I have chosen.
晚安
Good night.
伊丽莎白！
Elizabeth!
我以为我失败了
I thought I had failed.
以为一切都完了 以为…
I thought it was entirely over. I thought…
我以为…
And I thought…
我…
And I…
对称性
The symmetry.
上帝创造的对称性 对
God's symmetry. Yes, yes.
找到了
Yes.
把电池放在淋巴系统上
Placing the battery above the lymphatic system.
我就这么找到了解题的关键
I had found the key.
再也没有什么能阻挡我了
Nothing could stop me now.
没有
Nothing.
别动！这堆尸体
No! No, do not take any bodies
顶上的和底部的都别搬 就搬我做了标记的
from the top or the bottom of the pile unless I mark them.
冰冻或腐败可能会破坏组织
Ice or rot may have destroyed the tissue.
就看中间的那些
Look only in the middle.
东西太多 会让人晕头转向 除非目标非常明确
Abundance can be disorienting unless one hones one's aim.
我想要个子高的 长手长脚的
I'm favoring tall specimens, long limbs.
划定范围 活就好干了
Scale will make the work easier.
我喜欢
I like that.
尽善尽美嘛
Perfection.
有什么不好呢 亲爱的男爵？
And why not, dear Baron?
确实 有什么不好呢？
Indeed, why not?
找到完整的人头
Look for a head that's intact.
搬到车上去
Put that one in the cart.
那个放那边
Set that one over there.
其他的送过来
Bring the others.
老天
Oh, good God.
劳驾
Do you mind?
大功告成
It is finished.
哈兰德先生！
Herr Harlander!
暴风雨要来了！
A storm is coming!
我的拐杖
My cane.
我的拐杖！
My cane!
我的拐杖 手柄打开
My cane, in the handle.
水银
Mercury.
-你病了吗？ -谢谢
-Are you ill? -Thank you.
是梅毒吗？
Is it… syphilis?
对 我快死了
Yeah, I'm dying.
一夜偷欢 终生服毒
One night with Venus, a lifetime with Mercury.
是这么说的吧？
Isn't that the phrase?
几期了？
What stage?
二期？
Secondary?
你我都清楚会怎么发展
We both know the precise schedule.
已经在啃噬我的骨头了
It starts to eat away my bones,
眼眶、脸颊、牙齿、下颌、颅骨 层层侵蚀 直到抵达大脑
orbital, cheek, teeth, jaw, skull, exposing my brain.
长瘤、发狂、剧痛
Tumors, madness, excruciating pain.
到某个清晨 我会开始尖叫 停不下来
One fine morning, I will start to scream and I will never stop.
我无法接受如此不堪地死去
I cannot face such a vulgar demise.
于是我想到了我唯一的要求
Which brings me to my one condition.
我们约定好的交易
Our deal. As agreed, in exchange
我为你慷慨解囊所能换取的东西
for my generous intervention on your behalf.
既然我们即将造出新人类
And as we give life to our new Adam,
我想要拥有这具完美新身体
I want to be placed in this new perfect body.
不行
No.
-不可以 -当然可以
-No, no. -Yes.
还没到时候！
Not now. Not now!
-正是这时候 -这事我们以后再聊 现在不行
-Precisely now. -We'll talk about this after, not now.
哪还有什么以后！
There is no after!
没有以后了
There is no after.
你要的一切 我都给你了！
I gave you everything you wanted!
你要什么 我都给你
I give you everything you ask for.
随你说
Name it, it's yours.
你要伊丽莎白都行
Even Elizabeth.
求你了
Please.
礼貌一点总有效果
"Please" always helps.
你已经病入膏肓了
The disease has spread all inside of you.
这是全身性疾病 你知道的
It's systemic, and you know it.
你的每个器官都感染了
Every organ in you is polluted.
大脑 血液 全都感染了
Your brain, your blood, it's all polluted.
但我还有钱啊 对不对？
But my money's not, is that it?
无济于事
It's impossible.
我只要你说一个“行”字
Now, all you need to say is one simple word.
别的什么都不要说
"Yes," no more and no less.
不行！听明白了吗？不行！
No! Do you understand? No!
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
住手！
Stop!
住手
Stop.
没了这个 我们就一无所有了 我们俩都会完蛋
If we lose that, we have nothing. We both lose.
普罗米修斯 我就是啄食你肝脏的鹰！
I will be the eagle that feasts on your liver!
求你了 住手！
Please, stop!
哈兰德先生！
Herr Harlander. Herr Harlander!
坚持住 看着我！
Hold on, look at me!
不！哈兰德先生
No! Herr Harlander!
不要啊
No, no. No!
不！
No, no, no!
No!
不！
No! No! No!
你骗了我
You lied to me.
骗了我
You lied.
维克多！
Victor!
别过来 求你了
No, please.
看 一样的
Look. Same.
太阳
Sun.
阳光
Sun. Light.
去感受一下
Face it.
阳光 太阳…
Sunlight. The sun is…
太阳是生命之源
The sun is life.
很温暖
Ah, the warmth. Huh?
没错
Yes! Yes.
维克多
Victor.
-维克多 -对
-Victor. -Yes.
对 你就是
Yes, yes, yes. Of course you are.
你当然就是
Of course you are.
维克多
Victor.
邮件来了
The mail, sir.
老庄园来的信
Letters from the old estate.
日内瓦
Geneva.
-有我叔叔的来信吗？ -没有
-Is there anything from my uncle? -No.
或许我们该去拜访一下他们了
Perhaps we should pay them a visit.
小心 看着脚下
Careful. Look. Look down.
水
Water. Water.
Water.
对 水
Yes, water.
-维克多 -不 我是维克多
-Victor. -No, I'm Victor.
这是水 来这里
That's water. Come here.
-维克多 -来吧 很好
-Victor. -Come now, come. All right, good.
要跨一大步
We're going to take a big step.
我们一起来 准备好了？
We'll do it together. Ready?
-走这边 这样 -维克多
This way, like this.
不是那样 走这边
No, not like that. This way.
别碰 烫
Oh, no, no, no. Hot, hot.
不能碰 别碰它
No, don't touch. Don't touch that.
烫
It's hot.
坐下 很好 真棒
Sit. Very good. Very good. Yes.
好 看这是什么
Yes. Now, look what I have here.
看这个 这是什么？
Look at this. What is this thing?
这个怪东西是什么？当心
What is this strange thing? Careful.
你力气很大
You're very strong.
好了 这样
Yes. And like this. Huh?
还想要那个？好 这个放这里
Yes, you want another? Yes, this one goes right here.
钥匙
Key.
维克多
Victor.
这样你就不会着凉了
This will keep you nice and warm.
披上一条好毯子 暖暖的
Nice blanket to keep you warm.
维克多
-Victor.
好了
All right.
你待在这里
You stay.
就待在这里
You stay here now.
待着别动
Stay here now.
我去去就回 待着别动
I'll be back. All right. Stay there.
维克多
Victor.
别动 没事的
No, no, no, no, no. It's all right.
我会回来的
I'll come back.
维克多
Victor.
对他来说 一切都是新的
Everything was new to him.
温暖、冰冷、阳光、黑暗
Warmth, cold, light, darkness.
我的任务是塑造他
And I was there to mold him.
造成之后的事 我还从未考虑过
I never considered what would come after creation.
来到世界尽头
And having reached the edge of the earth,
才发现没有地平线
there was no horizon left.
如此成就有种非自然的感觉
The achievement felt unnatural.
并无意义
Void of meaning.
这让我十分烦恼
And this troubled me so.
船员们都想回去
Your men, they wish to go back.
对吗？
Yes?
可能吧
Probably.
不过一旦船能开动 我们就会继续前行
But the moment we're free, we're setting sails forwards.
不管付出什么代价
No matter the cost.
你简直和我一样疯狂
You share my madness.
我向你讲述自己的故事 或许别有深意
Perhaps there is a finer point in me telling you my story.
男爵 不管是否如此
Whether there is or isn't, Baron…
我都愿意听
I'd like to hear it.
几周过去了
Weeks passed,
他的力量迅速增强 我却日渐衰弱
and as his strength increased rapidly, mine waned.
可惜他没学会更多的话 也没有别的进展
Alas, no further language or development occurred.
不对
No, no, no, no, no, no.
低头
Down, down, down, down.
这就对了
Yes, there we are.
可以了 别动
There we are. Stay there. Stay.
这就是你
Yes, that's you.
这是你 知道了吗？
That's you. All right?
愈合得很好
Oh, yes, this is healing rather nicely.
我累了
I'm tired.
我好久没睡了
I have not slept.
一点都没睡
Not a winky-dinky-doo of sleep for me.
一直在照顾你
Tending to you.
终于给你脸上刮干净了
I've finished shaving you.
不行 别动
No, no, stop, stop.
放下 不可以 松开
Let go. No, no, no, no, no, no. Open.
手松开 快松开
Open your hand. Open. Open it.
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
看看你都干了什么
Look. Look what you've done.
你要听我的话 我说了放下
You have to listen to me. You have to listen. I said drop it.
真蠢！不 别这样
Stupidity! No. Stop.
来
Come here.
-维克多 -不 别碰我！
-Victor. -No, don't touch me!
永远都别碰我！
Don't ever touch me!
来吧
Come here.
不是我 是你自己弄的
I didn't do this. You did this.
伤口
The wound.
闭合了
It's closed.
怎么会的
But how?
好了
All right.
不行
No, no, no.
别动
No.
好了
All right. All right.
肯定一切都好
I'm sure everything's all right.
很快就到了
We'll be there soon enough.
我知道你有想法 我知道
I know you have thoughts. I know.
我知道你有
I know you do.
就在这里面 你有想法
Somewhere in there. Somewhere in there you have thoughts.
是不是？
Hmm? Don't you?
你想说什么吗？
Something you might want to say?
虽然脑子里很乱、很困惑
However jumbled, however confused?
有想法吗？
Hmm? Something?
还是我太心急了？
Am I presuming too much?
维克多
Victor.
知道了！
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes!
这个已经教会你了
This much we have established.
那是我的名字 我的名字是维克多
That is my name. My name is Victor.
你还能说点别的吗？什么都可以
Is there anything else that you can say? Anything at all? Hmm?
有吗？
Anything? Anything?
太阳
Um, sun, hmm?
冷、雨、血 任何东西
Cold. Rain. Blood. Anything.
靴子 靴子会说吗？
Boot. Can you say "boot"?
维克多
Victor.
够了！那么…
No, yes, no, yes! How about…
手呢？手会说吗？
How about "hand"? Can you say "hand"?
手 说啊…
Hand. Hand.
你这是怕我吗？
Oh. Oh, oh. You are afraid of me?
你怕我？
You're afraid of me?
为什么？为什么你会怕我？
Why? Why would you be afraid of me?
我不会伤害你的
I'm not going to hurt you.
我不会伤害你的 是我造了你
I'm not going to hurt you. I made you.
是我造了你！别这样了！
I'm your maker! Stop it!
你们来了 真的来了
You're here. You're really here.
来吧 快进来
Come on, then. Come, come.
伊丽莎白 我得说 我有好多东西要给你看
I have to tell you. I have so much to show you, Elizabeth.
特别奇妙 你都不敢相信
You won't believe it. It's absolutely marvelous.
快来 先给你看我的笔记
Come, come, I'll show you my notes first.
我叔叔在这里吗？
Is my uncle here?
什么？
What?
我叔叔 他在这里吗？
My uncle, is he here?
不在
No, no.
这里就我一个人 他不在
No, I'm alone. He's not here.
-他…他几天后会回来 -维克多 你看着状态不大好
-He's… He'll be back in a few days. -You don't look very well, Victor.
我的状态从来没这么好过！ 我的头脑清晰多了！快来！
Oh, I've never felt better! I've never had a clearer mind! Come, come!
你发烧了吗？
Are you running a fever?
我只是看到你太激动了
I am just very excited to see you.
我太高兴了 简直要飞起来了
I'm exalted. The spirits have lifted me so much.
那东西太神奇了 我就知道能实现
Absolutely marvelous…
维克多
Victor…
维克多 请给我一点时间
Victor. Victor.
是谁伤害了你？
Who hurt you?
威廉 你一定要看看这个
I have to show you this, William.
我先整理一下
Let me organize it for you.
我也有东西要给你看
And I have something to show to you.
我跟英国皇家医学会的人聊过了
I've spoken to the Royal Medical Society.
-他们想见你 -现在还不行
-They're interested in seeing you. -No, no, no, not yet.
我还没准备好
I'm not quite ready yet.
我以为这是你一直以来的梦想
I thought that's what you always wanted.
那个男人
The man.
-楼下的那个男人 -你看到他了？
-The man downstairs. -You saw him?
他是病人吗？是被你打伤的吗？
Is he a patient? A victim?
他身上好多伤口 你竟然下手那么重
His wounds. You wounded him like that.
不 伤害他的是这个世界 伊丽莎白
No, no, no. It was the world that hurt him, Elizabeth.
我给了他生命
I… I gave him life.
I gave him life.
起来
Up, up, up.
来
Come on.
慢着
There, there, there…
他还在适应周围的环境
He's still getting used to his surroundings.
它很强壮 威廉
It is strong, William.
-你成功了 -非常强壮
-You did it. -It's so strong.
你成功了
You did it.
体内所有系统都正常运作
All its systems are functional.
伤口都在愈合
All healing.
愈合的状态不稳定
And the healing is erratic, yes.
但是非同寻常
But exceptional.
他为什么被拴在这里？
Why is he chained here?
为了保护他自己 还有我
For his own safety and for mine,
也更方便给它清洁维护
and it's easy to clean and, uh, maintain it.
很多事它还不懂
And it doesn't know any better.
但你懂
But you do.
哈兰德知道了吗？
Does Harlander know?
我们要在他回来之前把一切准备好…
We have to prepare everything for the moment he returns.
-当然 -…让一切都有模有样
-Of course. -And have everything presentable.
它有智慧吗？
Is it intelligent?
维克多 它有智慧吗？
Victor, is it intelligent?
我无法理解你是怎么做到的
I can't fathom how exactly you did what you did,
但这无疑是一项壮举
but its dimension does not escape me.
维克多 你有没有问过自己
Victor, did you ever ask yourself,
这个人的所有组成部分中
of all the parts that make that man,
哪块是灵魂藏身的地方？
which one holds the soul?
我没问过
No, I didn't.
楼下那头怪物总让人感到不安
There's something so disquieting about that creature down there.
扭曲诡异 像个在哈哈镜里探头探脑的身影
Askew, like a figure peeking around a funhouse mirror.
但很有活力
But animated.
是哪里来的活力？
Animated by what?
痛吗？
Does it hurt?
叶子？
A leaf?
给我的吗？
For me?
谢谢
Thank you.
是不是很美？
Isn't it beautiful?
给我的吗？
This is for me?
我是伊丽莎白
I'm Elizabeth.
会说吗？伊丽莎白
Can you say "Elizabeth"?
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
从喉咙里发出声音
My throat makes sounds.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
我要走了
I'm going to go now.
伊丽莎…白
Eliza… beth.
你不该靠近那东西的
You should not go near it.
那东西？
"It"?
没错 那东西
It. Yes.
那东西是活的 但没有智慧的火花
I believe there is life in it, but not the spark of intelligence
我故意这么设计的
that I had intended.
可能不是你想象的那样
Perhaps not as you understand it.
什么地方出了差错
Something went wrong.
阻塞了 缝合了 连通了
A blockage, a suture, a connection.
伟大的维克多·弗兰肯斯坦 还会犯错？
You, the great Victor Frankenstein, you made a mistake?
那头怪物只会一个词 仅有的一个
The Creature knows but one word, and one word alone.
维克多
"Victor, Victor, Victor, Victor."
只是莫名其妙地机械重复
It just parrots it without rhyme or reason.
也许在当下 那个词就是他的一切
Perhaps for the time being that word means everything to him.
要是重生后的他 获得活力的源泉其实更简单
What if in being anew, the spirit that animates him is simpler,
-更纯粹… -纯粹？
-purer-- -Purer?
比普通人的更纯粹呢？
Purer than that of the common man?
要是他不受制于原罪
What if, unrestrained by sin,
而造物主为这具伤痕累累的血肉之躯 直接注入了生气呢？
our creator's breath came into its wounded flesh directly?
天啊 伊丽莎白
Good God, Elizabeth.
要是我强迫自己信了你这话
If I could force myself to believe it,
我会觉得你是不是被这东西吸引了
it would be my inclination to see attraction in you for that thing.
好好理解一下
Understanding.
他的眼中有痛苦的情绪
In those eyes I saw pain,
没有智慧 何来痛苦？
and what is pain if not evidence of intelligence?
那我的痛苦算什么？
What about my pain?
被你拒绝算什么？
What about what you have denied me?
我的心想要什么？
What my heart wants…
你的心？
Your heart?
所有人体结构中
Of all the human anatomy,
只有心最难捉摸
that is the organ furthest from your understanding.
男爵 只有怪物会扮演上帝
Only monsters play God, Baron.
比普通人更纯粹
Purer than the common man, hmm?
不知怎的 我成了坏人
And I, somehow, the villain. Mm-hmm.
你的心很纯粹？
Your heart is pure?
我向你保证 并非如此
I assure you it isn't.
我知道 因为是我亲手放进去的
I should know. I put it there.
上去
Up.
再试一下
Let us try again.
腿伸出来
Now give me your leg.
腿！
Leg!
腿伸出来！
Give me your leg!
没有智慧 何来痛苦？
Pain is evidence of intelligence, is it not?
行 测试一下这个说法吧
Well, let's test the theory.
腿伸出来！
Give me your leg!
腿！
Leg!
快点！
Come on!
伸出来 你个野兽！
Give it to me, you beast!
腿伸出来！
Give me your leg!
腿！
Leg!
维克多！
Victor!
Victor! Victor!
维克多 怎么了？
What is it, Victor?
来
Come. Come.
我失败了 我犯了大错
I failed. I made a mistake.
-你没有失败 我看过你的图纸了 -失败了
-No, you didn't fail. I saw your papers. -I did.
-非常完美 -那头怪物极其危险
-It's perfect. -The Creature is extremely dangerous.
没有…维克多
There's not… Victor.
我们等哈兰德回来 再一起讨论吧
Let's wait for Harlander and discuss together.
威廉 有件事我得告诉你
William, there is something you should know.
我得给你看一下
Something I have to show you.
-哈兰德… -那头怪物突然暴怒 把他杀了
-Ha-- Harlander… -In a fit of rage, he killed him.
这下你知道 我为什么没有及时告诉你了吧？
Do you understand now why I was hesitant to share this with you?
当然也不敢让伊丽莎白知道
And certainly not with Elizabeth.
那现在怎么办？
S… So what's to be done now?
什么？
What?
-现在怎么办？ -你说怎么办？
-What's to be done? -"What's to be done"?
你得带伊丽莎白回维也纳
You must take Elizabeth back to Vienna.
就说出了急事 必须马上走
Tell her something urgent came up and you have to leave immediately.
千万别让她知道
Keep her in the dark.
这是为了保护她
For her own safety.
必须照我说的办
You have to do as I say.
我们很快就回来 但现在只能先走
We'll be back in no time. But for now, this is for the best.
请上马车吧
Now get in the carriage, please.
你觉得那头怪物能活多久？
The Creature, what's its lifespan, you think?
必然没多久
Brief. Very brief, I'm sure.
我有种很坏的预感
I have the most terrible feeling.
怎么了？
What is it?
让马车回头
Turn the carriage around.
你一个人去维也纳吧
You go to Vienna.
让马车回头 否则我就跳车 他要杀了他
Turn the carriage around or I will jump. He's going to kill him.
说个词吧
Say one word.
再说一个 随便什么
One word more. Anything.
你说了 我就不杀你
Make me save you.
维克多
-Victor. -Mm-hmm.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
维克多！
Victor! Victor!
Victor!
维克多！
但故事并未结束
But that was not the end of it.
我试着创造生命 结果造就了死亡
In seeking life, I created death.
看来又要和他们聊聊了
It would seem I need to address my men again.
别担心
Don't worry.
他们会听我的话的
They'll listen to me.
住手！别伤害他！我在这里
No, no, stop! Do not harm him! I'm here.
带走我吧
Take me.
来吧 野兽
Go on, beast.
把我俩都杀了 证明造你的人说的都是真的
Kill us both. Confirm your maker's tale.
造我的人 说了他的故事
My maker… told his tale.
那我也来说说我的
Then I will tell you mine.
（第二部分 那头怪物的故事）
维克多！
Victor!
我反复呼唤你的名字 终于发现这里只有我
I called your name and understood I was alone.
-那是什么？ -开枪！
-What is that? -Shoot at it!
开枪！
Shoot it!
打到了吗？
Did you get it?
去哪了？
Where is it?
身上的伤口愈合了
My wounds had healed.
但我觉得寒冷刺骨
But I felt cold, so cold.
-能把火生起来吗？ -好
-Can you start the fire? -All right.
我会尽快把畜栏修好
And I'll repair the corral as soon as I can.
你没事吧 打到了吗？
You all right, then? Did you get it?
没有 我们到处看了 就是找不到
Nah, we looked everywhere. Couldn't find that thing.
虽然我们朝它开了两枪
Though we shot at it two times.
血迹在离这里一公里多的地方消失了
Blood trail died about a mile from here.
好 进来吧
All right. Come in. Come in.
我们跟了它一段时间 接着它就消失了
We followed it for a while and then it disappeared. Gone.
那是什么东西？熊吗？
What was it? Was it a bear?
不是熊 也不是人类 我从没见过那样的东西
That was no bear or human. I've never seen anything like it.
那么是幽灵吗？
Was it a ghost, then?
不是 它流血了 说明它有血肉 有骨头
It was no ghost. We drew blood. It was flesh and bone.
来这边
Come, come. Over here.
你还看到了什么
Tell me more about what you saw.
安娜玛丽亚 带祖父去壁炉边
Anna-Maria, take your grandfather over by the fireplace.
让他暖一暖
Make sure he's comfortable.
到这边来 祖父
Over here, Grandfather.
我们钻到了森林深处 还是没找到它
We went deep into the forest. Couldn't find it.
会抓到它的
We will get it.
-就是要花些时间 -好
-It'll take time. -Yeah.
安娜玛丽亚 过来
Anna-Maria, come.
宝贝 来带我出去
Come, love. Help me outside.
那位老人触动了我
The old man moved me.
他失明的双目充满智慧
And his unseeing eyes were full of wisdom.
这些人会发出一种声音
These people possessed a sound.
用来和彼此
Used it to tell each other
交流感受和想法
about feelings and ideas.
他们把这种声音叫言语
They called them words.
注意看
Pay attention.
这是什么？
What is this?
一个男孩
A boy.
-再说一遍 -一个男孩
-And again. -A boy.
很好 孩子
Very good, my child.
这个呢？
And this?
一只…一只眼睛
An… An eye.
-再说一遍 -一只眼睛
-And again. -An eye.
很好 乖孩子
Yeah. Well done. Well done, my girl.
-眼睛 -这个呢？
-Eye. -And this one?
手
The hand.
-很好 -手
-Very good. -Hand.
来搭把手
Give us a hand.
用绳子把最大的捆住带回去
Tie a rope around the biggest one back there.
我渴望加入这个家庭
I longed to be part of this family.
冬天之前要再多储备一些柴火
We'll need more kindling before the winter.
我们得跑几趟
We'll take a few trips.
渴望帮他们的忙
To be their benefactor.
需要大一点的树干来搭这个
We'll need larger trunks for the structure.
好
All right.
我能为他们做点什么呢？
What could I possibly do for them?
安娜玛丽亚！父亲！
Anna-Maria! Father!
快来看啊！
Come! Come and see!
看啊 安娜玛丽亚！
Look, Anna-Maria!
看 还有呢！快看！
Look, there's more! Look!
这会是谁送来的？
Who could have done this?
是森林精灵
The Spirit of the Forest.
我们得谢谢他
We should thank him.
谢谢你
Thank you.
说“谢谢你 森林精灵”
Say, "Thank you, Spirit of the Forest."
谢谢你 森林精灵
Thank you. Thank you, Spirit of the Forest.
谢谢
Thank you.
来吧 看这里
Come. Look over here.
谢谢你
Thank you.
从此以后 我就成了 他们看不见的守护者
From then on, I became their invisible guardian.
森林精灵
The Spirit of the Forest.
他们也不时对我释放小小的善意
And on occasion, they too extended a small kindness towards me.
送上衣服、面包
Clothes, bread.
在那段时光
And for a moment,
极为短暂的时光
a brief, brief moment,
我和这个世界相安无事
the world and I were at peace.
跟上
Come along. Come along.
进去吧 对
In you go. Yeah.
记得关门
Make sure you close that gate.
是谁做的呢？
Who could have done this?
森林精灵吧
The Spirit of the Forest, eh?
我知道了
I got it.
“最终 这个骄傲的年轻男子
"And in the end, the proud young man
再也找不到他丢失的那只手了
could never find his missing hand."
它变成了石头 他的财富消失了
"It turned to stone, his fortune gone,
他的骄傲 他的土地 都失去了”
and he lost his pride and lost his land."
非常好 宝贝
Very good, my dear.
读得真棒 再读下这个吧
Beautifully read. Now try this one.
狼来了
Wolves.
某个想法
An idea,
某种感觉 在我心中愈发清晰
a feeling became clear to me.
猎人并不憎恨狼
The hunter did not hate the wolf.
狼并不憎恨羊
The wolf did not hate the sheep.
但相互之间的暴力冲突无可避免
But violence felt inevitable between them.
我想 也许这正是世界的法则
Perhaps, I thought, this was the way of the world.
你成为猎物 被杀
It would hunt you and kill you
只是因为你的身份
just for being who you are.
父亲 我月末就会把羊卖掉
The sheep will be sold by the end of the month, Father.
然后带着你 阿尔玛和安娜玛丽亚去镇上住
Then I'll take you, Alma and Anna-Maria into town.
我们要上山
We'll go into the mountains,
去猎几头狼 冬末回来
hunt the wolves and be back at the end of winter.
我每年冬天都在这里祈祷 今年也一样
I pray here alone every winter and this year will be no different.
父亲 求你了 听劝吧
Please, Father, listen to reason.
你们该怎么做就怎么做 我也一样
You do what you must and so will I.
老顽固
You stubborn old goat.
现在只有你和我了 森林精灵
It's just you and I now, Spirit.
就你和我了
Just you and I.
我已经构想了无数种方式
And I had formed in my imagination many ways
我要在这个老头面前现身
I would present myself to the old man.
他会怕我？
Would he fear me?
欢迎我？
Welcome me?
还是会赶我走呢？
Turn me away?
谁在那里？
Who goes there?
上前一步 我进入了完全不同的世界
With a single step, I entered a different world.
曾经我只能远远观望的世界
One I had only seen from afar.
到底是谁？
Please, who is it?
出个声吧
Answer me.
告诉我
Tell me.
你来干什么的？
Why are you here?
路过
Travel.
亲爱的过客 欢迎你
Welcome, dear traveler.
请你自己找把椅子 不要觉得我怠慢了你
Do not think me ungrateful for the company if I ask you to procure a chair.
我没法周到待客
I… I find it difficult being a good host.
没错
Yes.
我的眼睛看不见
My… My sight has failed me.
桌上有面包和白兰地
But there is bread and brandy on the table.
请自行享用
Pray help yourself.
白兰地？
Bran… dy?
听你说话
Your language.
好像不大流利
You have a hard time speaking it.
你是不是从别的地方来的？
Are you not from these parts?
你害怕吗？
Are you afraid?
不用怕
No need to be.
你在怕什么？
What are you afraid of?
什么都怕
-Everything.
你的…
-Your…
你的手好冷
Your hands are frozen
你还受伤了
and you've been hurt, have you not?
受伤？
Hurt?
没错 你的手上和脸上都有伤疤
Yes. Your hands and face have scars
你还穿着制服
and you are wearing uniform.
是在战斗中受的伤吗？
Were you injured in battle?
你一直
You were hiding
躲在磨坊齿轮里面 对吧？
in the mill gears, were you not?
对 你就是森林精灵
Yeah. Yeah. The Spirit of the Forest.
没错
Yes.
我看不到你的面容
I cannot judge of your countenance,
但听你的嗓音
but there is something in your voice
你肯定很善良
which persuades me of your goodwill and kindness.
善良？
-Kindness? -Mm.
留下来吧
Stay with me.
你可以吃我的东西 烤我的火
Share my food and fire.
我有的不多 但能跟你分享 我会很高兴的
I would be delighted to share what little I have with you
有你陪着我 对我也大有好处
and would be greatly helped by your companionship.
你可以读书给我听
And you… you could read to me.
读书？
-Read? -Mm.
把这里当成自己家 把我当成朋友
Make this your home and I your friend.
朋友
Friend.
Friends.
就是在那时 我读到了我生命中第一个故事
And it was then that I read my first story,
也是《圣经》中的第一个故事
and it was the first story.
故事的主人公是一个名叫亚当的男子 和名叫夏娃的女子
I read about a man named Adam and a woman named Eve,
他们住在人类的第一个乐园里
about their time in the first garden.
我读到了两座城市崛起 相互竞争
I read about the rise of rival cities
一座高塔倒塌
and the collapse of a tower
上帝震怒毁城
and the wrath of a God.
我读到人类斗巨龙
And I read about men that fought dragons
最终失去一切
and men who lost everything.
时光流逝
And time passed
如秋叶飘落
and fell away with the leaves of autumn.
亲爱的朋友 你见过下雪吗？
Have you never seen the snow, my dear friend?
大雪荡涤一切 让世界焕然一新
It makes the world clean… and new.
“吾乃奥兹曼迪亚斯 万王之王
"My name is Ozymandias, King of Kings."
盖世功业 敢叫天公折服
"Look on my works, ye Mighty, and despair."
此外无一物
"No thing beside remains."
但见废墟周围 寂寞平沙空莽莽
"Round the decay of that colossal wreck, boundless and bare."
伸向荒凉的四方
"The lone and level sands stretch far away."
吾乃奥兹曼迪亚斯”
"My name is Ozymandias…"
世上哪里的书比这里还多？
Are there more books than this in the world?
肯定还有一些地方
A few more, I'm sure.
不是这里
Not here.
左边最后 就拿那本
Last book on the left. Take it.
那本还没读过
We haven't got to it.
弥尔顿的《失乐园》
Paradise Lost, Milton.
人类对上帝有疑问
Man has questions for God.
就连上帝自己也有疑问
Even God has questions.
我觉得上帝也想得到答案 所以才会派来自己的儿子
I think he wanted answers and that is why he sent us his son.
或许他很想了解死亡
Death probably intrigued him.
了解受苦受难
Suffering.
我想知道我是谁
I want to know who I am.
我从哪里来？
Where do I come from?
上帝拿走了你的记忆 而我多么希望我的记忆也被带走
God took your memory just as I wish he would take mine away.
多年前 我拿走了某个人的生命
Many years ago, I took a man's life.
那是个好人
A good man.
自那时起 我一直在赎罪
And I have been atoning for it since.
试着原谅
Forgive.
试着忘记
Forget.
智慧真正的试金石
The true measure of wisdom.
是知道自己受了伤害
To know you have been harmed,
知道被谁伤害
by whom you have been harmed,
然后选择让一切烟消云散
and choose to let it all fade.
但记不起来的东西 要怎么忘记
But I cannot forget what I cannot remember.
你什么都记不起来吗？
Do you recall nothing?
在睡梦中
In my dreams…
我…能窥见记忆
…I… see memories.
各种各样的人
Different men.
都是…一些片断
All… pieces.
我…
I…
我记得有火 有水
I remember f… fire and water.
脚下有沙子
And sand under my feet.
还有一个词
And a word.
就一个词
A single word.
什么词？
What is it?
维克多
Victor.
去找到它
Go to it.
维克多
The word.
然后我终于体会到了
And then I learned it.
真相的可怖
The horror of the truth.
我明白了 自己一无是处
I understood that I was nothing.
是个可怜虫
A wretch.
是块不起眼的污渍
A blot.
甚至算不上是人类
Not even of the same nature as man.
这种痛苦缠绕着我
This hurt clung to my mind.
永不消散
It never let go.
然后我看见了
Then I saw it.
你的名字
Your name.
“维克多·弗兰肯斯坦”
"Victor Frankenstein."
知道了到哪里能找到你
And where to find you.
不！
No!
你回来了
You came back.
我知道我是谁了
I found what I am.
知道我是什么造就的了
What I am made from.
我…我是尸骨堆里造出来的
I am… the child of a charnel house.
我是残骸
A wreckage.
是用垃圾和被丢弃的尸体拼凑出来的
Assembled from refuse and the discarded dead.
是怪物
A monster.
我知道你是谁
I know what you are.
你是个好人
A good man.
也是我的朋友
And… you are my friend.
朋友？
Friend?
朋友
Friend.
那是什么？
What is that thing?
是森林里的那东西吗？
The-- The thing from the woods?
你把他怎么了？
What have you done to him?
别动
Don't move.
快！上膛！杀了它！
Quick! Reload! Kill it!
一切重回寂静
There was silence again,
而冷酷无情的生活还将继续
and then… merciless life.
我死了多久？
How long did I die for?
不知道
I do not know.
但我看到身上的伤口愈合了
But I saw my injuries healed.
冬日的寒风直灌入肺
The cold winter air stung in my lungs.
孤独感更甚以往 且前所未有
I felt lonelier than ever,
因为对世人而言 治愈一切痛苦的良药
because for every man there was but one remedy to all pain:
唯有死亡 而这恩赐你也狠心剥夺
Death, a gift you too had denied me.
我的内心涌起羡慕之情
Envy rose within me
遂决意向你索求一份恩典
and decided to demand a single grace from you.
我的缔造者
My creator.
我想要…一个同伴
I would demand… a companion.
起来吧
I need you to get up.
好的
Yes, of course. Of course.
婚礼马上要开始了 你得陪在我身边
The wedding will start soon and I want you by my side.
要不是你天性善良
It's hard to believe,
我都不敢相信这话是你说的
if not for your kind nature.
我跟几位宾客说了调查的事
I've spoken to a few guests about the inquest.
关于那场爆炸的调查
About the explosion.
他们中的大多数都接受了官方的说法
The majority accept it for what it was.
官方怎么说 威廉？
And what was it, William?
都过去了 维克多
The past, Victor.
那是场可怕的意外
A terrible accident.
我想卖了那座庄园
I intend to sell the estate.
我们只有彼此了
All we have is each other.
往四面八方撒
I want you to throw the petals everywhere.
到处都撒一点
Throw them everywhere.
到楼上去 再多撒点
Go upstairs and do some more of that.
我知道 婚礼前见新娘会带来厄运
I know it is bad luck to see the bride before the ceremony.
只对新郎起效
Only for the groom.
没错 对我没用
Yes, that's right. Not for me.
你好啊 伊丽莎白
Hello, Elizabeth.
之前我从未感受过懊悔 而现在懊悔充斥了我的内心
I've rarely felt remorse before and now I feel little else. I…
我的心被一种冲动占据已久 但这种感觉已经消散
A fever gripped me for so long, but it has passed,
我可以正常地面对你了
and I see you now as I should.
无论如何 我衷心祝愿
For whatever it's worth, I… I wish you and my little brother,
你和我挚爱的弟弟幸福
who I love more than life, the very best.
你大可以自欺欺人
You may like to believe you do.
而我都害怕听见
And I dread to even hear it.
今天是我的大喜之日 我就求你一件事
On my wedding day, I ask you but for a single grace.
别撒谎了
No more lies.
-我想告诉你… -给我出去
-I-- I want to tell you-- -Leave my chambers now.
-伊丽莎白 -出去！
-Elizabeth. -Leave!
出来 别躲在暗处
Come out of the shadows,
如果你在这里
if you are here.
你是来感谢我的吗？
Are you here to thank me?
你活下来了 还变得足够聪明 都找到我了
You survived and are intelligent enough to have found me.
是我造得好
I made you well.
我要你给我造一个同伴
I need you to make a companion for me.
像我这样的
One like me.
同伴？
A com… A companion?
我知道了
I see.
再来个怪物
Another monster.
对
Yes.
让我们两个怪物作伴
We can be monsters together.
我付出巨大代价 才找回了理智
I have found sanity at such a cost,
你却想让我再回疯狂
and you here… are madness calling me back.
我死不了
I cannot die.
只有我自己
And I cannot live…
我也活不好
alone.
我造出了非常恐怖的东西
In you I have created something truly horrible.
不是东西
Not something.
是人
Someone.
你造出了人
You made someone.
就是我
Me.
不管我多么让人费解 但我会思考
Whatever puzzle I am, creator, I think.
有感受
I feel.
我只有这一个请求
I have this sole petition…
再造一个像我一样的
Make one like me.
然后呢？
And then what?
生育
Procreation.
繁殖
Reproduction.
建立家庭？
A home?
建造坟墓？
A grave?
死亡与破坏不断上演
Death begetting death begetting death.
恶魔的种族在地球上蔓延
A race of devils propagated upon the earth.
肮脏永不断绝
Obscenity perpetuating itself.
在你看来我很肮脏 在我看来我只是我
I am obscene to you, but to myself I simply am.
滚开！
Begone!
我绝不会再造一个 像你这么邪恶丑陋的东西
Never again will I make something like you, wicked and deformed.
这一切还不都是 源自你的执念 维克多
Then it is still all about your will, Victor.
凭恐怖的执念造就我 如今又固执地谴责我
That horrible, horrible will that birthed me condemns me now?
我开口说话算不上奇迹 你愿意倾听才算！
The miracle is not that I should speak, but that you would ever listen!
你不愿赐我伴侣 我将倾泻怒火
If you are not to award me love, then I will indulge in rage.
无穷无尽的怒火
And mine is infinite.
请让一让
Step aside.
维克多
Victor.
怎么了？
What's going on?
你
You…
是你
It's you.
伊丽莎白 离它远一点！
Elizabeth, move away from it!
不要！
No!
那东西袭击了她！
It attacked her! It attacked her!
带我走吧
Take me with you.
天啊
Oh, my God!
别动 让我来…我能救你
No, let me… I can save you.
我会救活你
I can save you.
救我？
From what?
是害我吧
From you?
我怕你 维克多
I fear you, Victor.
不
No, no…
一直怕你
I always have.
你的每一次疯狂和破坏
Every ounce of madness and destruction.
如同大火 足以吞噬一切
The very conflagration that devoured everything.
一切都是你造成的
It all came from you.
你才是怪物
You are the monster.
我和这个世界格格不入
My place was never in this world.
我一直渴望并追寻着 一种说不清道不明的东西
I sought and longed for something I could not quite name.
可在你身上 我找到了这种东西
But in you, I found it.
丢失并被寻回
To be lost and to be found,
这就是爱的宿命
that is the lifespan of love.
其短暂
And in its brevity,
其悲剧性
its tragedy…
造就永恒
this has been made eternal.
就让我在你的注视之中
Better this way… to fade…
死去吧
with your eyes gazing upon me.
她走了 我也想随她而去
She is gone and I long to follow.
你给了我备受唾弃的生命
You gave me life unwanted.
我这就还给你
I give that back to you.
你当我是怪物
You thought me a monster.
就让我这个怪物来回敬你
Now I return the favor.
杀了我 现在就杀了我
Kill me! Kill me now, do it!
我要让你流血
I will make you bleed.
让你卑微求饶
I will make you humble.
你是造了我
You may be my creator,
但从今天起 你要听我的话
but from this day forward, I will be your master.
你为了猎杀我
You hunted me past the forests,
翻山越岭
past the mountains,
横跨冰川
past frozen horizons,
直到天地间
until there was nothing left.
只剩你我
Just you… and me.
给我来点子弹
I need ammunition.
这个磨快一点
Sharpen this.
来三罐炼乳 一点木柴
Three cans of condensed milk, some firewood.
还有六筒炸药
And six sticks of dynamite.
六筒？
Six?
你要打什么？
What are you hunting?
大的
Big game.
不！
No! No! No!
维克多
Victor.
只有被我伤到 你才会听我说话
You only listen when I hurt you.
这个 你相信这东西
This. You put your faith in this.
能够摧毁我
You think this will unmake me.
点着吧 希望如你所愿 但如果失败了
Light it then and hope it does, but if it does not,
我会再来找你
I will come for you again.
点起来！
Light it!
快跑吧
Now… run.
好了 如今你残破不堪
So, there you were, broken and discarded.
而我
And I,
又活过来了
alive again.
我能感到 被灼伤的血肉在重新生长
I could feel my singed flesh regrowing.
断裂的骨头重回原位
The crackling of my bones resetting.
永不停息的心脏泵出汩汩的血流
The murmur of my blood pumping through my incessant heart.
再次发现无人怜悯
And once more finding no mercy,
我只剩一条路可走
I had but one path.
我们终究走到了这一步
And here we are.
精疲力尽 一无所有
Spent and done.
再没有什么可以付出或索取了
No more in us to give or take.
帐篷外的血迹
The blood outside the tent…
是我的
It is mine.
都是我的
All mine.
我将流血
I will bleed.
疼痛
Ache.
受苦
Suffer.
永无尽头
You see, it will never end.
对不起
I am sorry.
我的内心充满懊悔
Regret consumes me.
如今我终于能正视我的生命了
And I now regard my life for what it was.
缔造者 你要走了
You will go now, creator.
要消失了
Fade away.
一切都只是短暂的一瞬
It will all be but a brief moment.
我的诞生 我的悲伤
My birth. My grief.
你的损失
Your loss.
我不会受惩罚
I will not be punished.
也无法摆脱罪责
Nor absolved.
我的希望
What hope I had,
我的怒火
what rage…
都毫无意义
It is all nothing.
那股造就我的浪潮 如今要带你走了
The tide that brought me here now comes to take you away.
留下搁浅的我
Leaving me stranded.
原谅我吧
Forgive me.
吾儿
My son.
如你有意 也请宽恕自己的存在
And if you have it in your heart, forgive yourself into existence.
吾儿 如果无法死去 还请细思此事
If death is not to be, then consider this, my son.
既然活着
While you are alive,
除了活下去 还有别的选择吗？
what recourse do you have but to live?
活着
Live.
说出我的名字吧
Say my name.
我的名字是父亲起的
My father gave me that name,
但其实并无意义
and it meant nothing.
现在 我请求你把这个名字还给我
Now I ask you to give it back to me…
最后一次了
one last time.
就像最开始 你把这个名字
The way you said it at the beginning.
当成全世界时那样呼唤我
When it meant the world to you.
维克多
Victor.
我宽恕你
I forgive you.
安息吧 父亲
Rest now, Father.
或许现在
Perhaps now,
我们都能算作是人了
we can both be human.
放下武器
Weapons down.
-放下武器 -我要为我的人负责
-Put the weapons down! -I am responsible for my men.
让他走
He can leave.
船能动了！
We are free!
我们自由了！
船长
Captain…
您的指令是？
What are your orders?
扬帆起航
Man the sails.
掉头
Turn around.
您要亲自宣布吗？
Do you want to tell the men?
大家听好！
Men!
我们开船回家
We're sailing home!
我们回家了
（“心会破碎 但破碎后依然跳动” 拜伦勋爵）
（基于玛丽·雪莱）
（所著小说《科学怪人》改编）
《科学怪人》
字幕翻译： 涅伽达